# 大家好 今天終於出太陽啦
Hi everyone! Finally, it's a sunny day.
# 我上山上看一有沒有那個野果
We're going onto the hill and see if there are any wild fruits.
# 看下它們的產量高不高
Let's see if the yield is high or not.
# 在這上面
It's up there.
# 今年應該很高的產量哦
The yield this year should be rather high, you know,
# 因為它開花的時候沒怎麼下雨
cuz it barely rained when the flowers blossomed.
# 你看 這個是吊deng po哦
Look! This is "diao deng po" (note: local wild fruits).
# 今年的產量特別高
The yield this year is exceptionally high.
# 一樹都是哦
They're all over the tree.
# 隨便找了棵樹都是那麼多的哦
And it's the same in any other tree.
# 所以 到了那個夏天的時候就有的吃啦
So, we're gonna have a feast when, you know, when summer comes.
# 這些都是小小的 幾百個哦
These are all very small. I see hundreds of them,
# 一顆[SIC]樹上有幾百個
hundreds of them in just one tree.
# 現在還沒熟 到時候來摘
They're still green now. We'll come again later.
# 這個就是
This is called,
# 我們這邊的方言叫re 萢子
it's called "re po le" in our dialect here.
# 它 這個應該也叫野草莓一樣的
It's, kind of, sort of like wild berries.
# 很好吃的哦 長 到熟了之後那麼大 紅的
It tastes really good. When they grow, I mean, become ripe, they'll become that big and turn red.
# 到時候就用那個 針草串起來一串一串的
Then we can make strings of them, using the needle grass.
# 特別好吃 特別甜
It's really tasty, really sweet.
# 今年也好多啊 到處都是 這個
There are also a lot this year. They're everywhere, see?
# 你看 現在都是青的 到熟了之後就紅的
Look! They're now green, and will turn red when they become ripe.
# 你看 這些
Look! These are,
# 像個小光頭一樣
just like a little skinhead.
# 好多
A lot!
# 這個荷蘭豆
These are snow peas.
# 這個花好靚的哦
The flowers are really beautiful,
# 像個小蝴蝶一樣
like a small butterfly.
# 這是隔壁老奶奶種的 你看
They belong to our neighbouring old lady.
# 八十多歲了 還種了那麼靚的菜
She's already in her eighties. But her veggies are still that beautiful.
# 這個不 就不能去摘了
We're not, we shouldn't pick them.
# 摘了就不厚道了
It would be too mean otherwise.
# 你看 今年長了好多枇杷果啊 一樹都是哦上面
Look! There are a lot of loquats this year. They're all over the tree up there,
# 一大片
everywhere.
# 你看 這裡好多梨花啊
Look! Here are a lot of pear flowers.
# 這是梨樹來的
This is a pear tree.
# 到時候又有梨吃了 這個兄弟家的 這個梨樹
We'll then have pears later. It belongs to my buddy, this pear tree.
# 還有 棕花
Here are also, palm flowers.
# 這樹上還有饅頭哦
There are also figs in this tree.
# 這個 饅頭 饅頭果
These are, figs, figs fruits.
# 做那個涼粉
They can be used to make jelly.
# 這是梨花哦 這個
These are pear flowers you know.
# 全是梨花 今年的梨
All are pear flowers, the pear this year.
# 哇
Wa!
# 兄弟家的老母雞
My buddy's old hens
# 我去看一下
Let me take a look,
# 看一下有沒有雞蛋檢
and see if there are any eggs for me.
# 你看這個雞 個個都四五斤的哦 這種雞
Look at these hens! Each weighs at least two kilograms, these hens.
# 很好吃的 又肥
They taste really good, and they're fat.
# 走了 回家啦
Alright! Let's go back home.
# 有甚麼好看的
What's so interesting there?
# 剛好路過兄弟家的大棚哦 看一上他種甚麼菜
We just pass by my buddy's big shed. Let's see what veggies he has.
# 誒 又是茄子
Eh! Eggplants again.
# 兄弟咋麼那麼喜吃茄子嘞
What made him like eggplants that much.
# 一百多個大棚哦
There are more than a hundred big sheds,
# 這裡
right here.
# 全是種的這個
But there's nothing but,
# 黃瓜跟這個茄子
cucumbers and, you know, eggplants.
# 這兄弟也不種點西瓜也可以呀 香瓜也好啊
Why doesn't this guy grow some melons, or watermelons, or whatever?
# 種點水果吃 好多啊
I mean, some fruits. It would certainly be really nice.
# 種這茄子
Eggplants,
# 只能當菜吃
they're just nothing more than veggies.
# 唉 怎麼那麼多茄子
Ay! Why on earth are there some many eggplants?
# 這個樹很好爬的哦
I think I can climb this tree very easily.
# 一跳就跳上去了
A single hop is all that's needed.
# 一跳就跳上去
# 這個梅子
This is a "meizi" (plum).
# 這在都好大了哦 差不多就可以摘啦
It's now very big and can be picked very soon.
# 到時候我們摘點來泡酒
We'll then pick some and infuse them into liquor.
# 哇 這個大
Wa! This one is big!
# 這個好大啊
This one is really big.
# 還沒熟 不摘掉
It's still green. I leave it here.
# 你看 這些
Look! These are,
# 都很大啦
already very big now.
# 差不多可以吃了
I can eat them very soon.
# 摘一個下來
Let me pick one.
# 你看
Look!
# 小小的
A tiny one
# 這就是這個青梅
This is exactly a green plum.
# 很靚的哦這個
It's really beautiful.
# 這個還不能吃
It's still not to be eaten.
# 嗯 這
Um! It's...
# 好苦
bitter!
# 不太熟
It's not ripe.
# 但這個梅子味
But it's really rich,
# 很十足哦
in the flavour of plum.
# 啊~受不了
Ah~ I can't stand it!
# 你看這個
Look at this one!
# 這個楊梅也開花了哦
The plum flowers have also blossomed.
# 好多啊
A lot!
# 開了小花
Small flowers
# 你看 這笋子都長出來啦
Look! The bamboo shoot is already coming out.
# 好多 這裡有一個
A lot! Here's one.
# 那裡有一個 還不大的
There's another one. That one is not that big.
# 你看 這裡有一個
Look! Here's one.
# 土都裂開啦 還有
The soil has already cracked open. One more,
# 這裡有一個
one more here.
# 好多啊 這笋子
They're everywhere, the shoots.
# 你看這個李子樹 有很多小李子哦
Have a loot at his "lizi" (plum) tree. There are a lot of small plums!
# 你看 很小的
Look! They're really small.
# 你看 這個 很小的這個李子
Look! Here, the plums are really small.
# 好多 一樹都是
A lot! All over the tree.
# 這個也是那個野生的哦 沒人要的
These are also, you know, wild, and don't belong to anyone.
# 就長在那個河邊上
They're just growing on the riverside.
# 到時候我們想摘的時候就來摘
We can come and pick some later whenever we want.
# 別人不會說我的
Nobody's gonna say anything.
# 轉了一圈 甚麼都沒找到
Now we're back, without finding anything.
# 我上山上挖個竹笋來烤
Let me go onto the hill, dig a bamboo shoot, and grill it.
# 山上竹笋已經冒出頭來了哦
The heads of the bamboo shoots there are already coming out.
# 一鋤頭就沒了
Put down the hoe, gone!
# (沒有原字幕)
Puppies!
# 你看 這裡有一個
Look! Here's one.
# 還太了啦
It's still too small.
# 去搞個大點啦
I'm gonna get a bigger one.
# 這裡有一個大的
Here's a big one!
# 你看 這個
Look! This is,
# 這個夠大的 這個
this is big enough, yea.
# 你看 啊 這個 那麼大的
Look! Ah! This one, is so big!
# 這個是春笋啊
This is a spring shoot, you know.
# 它長大就是一棵竹子
I would become a bamboo if it grows up.
# 不能挖那麼多 挖一個就夠了
I can't get too many. Just one is enough.
# 你看 這個
Have a look at it!
# 我拿回去
I'm gonna take it back,
# 拿去去烤
take it back and grill it.
# 夠了
Enough
# 一個就夠了
One is already enough.
# 那麼大
It's that big.
# 高壓水槍一樣的
It's just like a high-pressure water gun.
# 一層一層的把它剝掉
I'm peeling it off layer by layer.
# 這是
These are,
# 剛長出來的莖
the stems that have just come out.
# 你看
Look!
# 很靚哦 這個
It's really beautiful!
# 這樣繼續剝
Keep peeling
# 肉好少的哦這個 肉就一點點
There's not so much to eat, just a tiny little bit.
# 就那麼一點點
Just a tiny little bit.
# 等下你少吃一點
So you're going to have less.
# 就這一點 哈哈
Just a bit here, ha ha!
# 把這個
I'm gonna...
# 你看 這個竹笋
Look! This bamboo shoot.
# 很靚哦 這個 等下就這樣 就這樣去烤
It's so beautiful! This, this can be, can be then grilled right away.
# 要不然把它對半先破開先
Or, shall I first, cut it into halves first?
# 你看 這聲音
Look! The sound!
# 好
Good!
# 哎呀 好香啊
Aya! It smells really nice!
# 把竹笋 把這個竹笋 把這個竹笋裏起來
Let me wrap, wrap the, wrap the bamboo shoot,
# 放到那個 火堆里面去
put it, into the fire,
# (沒有原字幕，我聽到好像是「煨」，都想把它譯了)
and grill it.
# 先把它烤 烤熟
Grill, grill it first.
# 烤熟之後我們再加上那個
They we can put some, you know,
# 加上孜然
put some cummin powder,
# 加上醬油
put some soy sauce.
# 就可以吃二
And then we can eat.
# 你看 就這樣 把它奶到那 火堆里面去
Look! Then, I can simply, throw it, into the fire.
# 放在這裡燒就可以了
Leave it here, grill it, that's it.
# 燒個二十多分鐘就夠了
Leaving it here for a good twenty minutes would be enough.
# 這熟了哦
It's alright now.
# 好香啊
It smells so good!
# 加點醬油就可以吃的 這個
With some soy sauce, it can be eaten right away.
# 這個太燙啦
It's too hot.
# 要等一下 放在這裡等一下再
Leave it here, leave it here for a while, and then,
# 等它熟了之後我再那個
When it's done, we'll, you know,
# 再去吃
we'll eat it.
# 火太燙啦
The fire is too hot.
# 變成竹笋乾了這個
It has become dried bamboo shoot.
# 火燒啦
It's burnt.
# 叫我弟看火看火
I asked my younger brother to watch the fire.
# 看著叫他看著別燒掉啦
Let it, I asked him not to let it burn.
# 就燒掉了
And now it's burnt.
# 靠不住啊
What an unreliable guy!
# 不能吃了
No, it's not edible.
# 打開來看一下這個能不能吃
Let me open it and see if it's edible.
# 好香啊
It smells so good!
# 真的很香
Really good!
# 嗯
Um!
# 還有竹子的甜味
There's still the sweetness of bamboo.
# 嗯 還可以哦
Um! It's not too bad!
# 還有竹子的那個清香味 在這裡面 竹笋的清香味
There's still the scent of bamboo, inside, the scent of bamboo shoot.
# 還可以吃
It's still edible.
# 嗯
Um!
# 可以哦 很香
Not bad! It smells really good!
# 很脆
And it's crunchy.
# 你們想不想吃
Do you guys want some?
# 這是素來的 你們不吃的
It's veggie. You don't like it.
# 你們吃肉
You guys eat only meat.
# 給你們吃了 不要啦
It's yours now. I don't want it anymore.
# 你看 這個皮都可以撕的下來
Look! It can be peeled.
# 好啦 給你們吃啦 不好吃
Alright! It's yours now! It tastes so bad.
# 快 快點吃掉啊
Come, c'mon! Finish it!
# 今晚給你們 這就是你們的晚餐 吃掉
Tonight you'll have...It's your dinner. Finish it!